<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://aggiebranczyk.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://aggiebranczyk.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-12-12T12:17:42+00:00</updated><id>https://aggiebranczyk.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Aggie Branczyk</title><subtitle>A physicist having fun in quantum tech. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Mr Beast Accountability Co-working Session #1</title><link href="https://aggiebranczyk.com/blog/2024/mr-beast-accountability-ai-assisted-coding/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mr Beast Accountability Co-working Session #1"/><published>2024-12-11T17:06:01+00:00</published><updated>2024-12-11T17:06:01+00:00</updated><id>https://aggiebranczyk.com/blog/2024/mr-beast-accountability-ai-assisted-coding</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://aggiebranczyk.com/blog/2024/mr-beast-accountability-ai-assisted-coding/"><![CDATA[<p>Today I’m joining a <a href="https://lu.ma/k9wclosu?tk=1yEyJQ">Mr Beast-style accountability co-working session</a> at <a href="https://buildersclub.ca">Builders Club</a>. It’s my first one. I’m planning to document my progress over the next three hours in this blog post. At the end of the three hours, I’m hitting publish.</p> <p>Briefly about the agenda:</p> <p>​ - <strong>2:00 PM:</strong> Round table check-in and goal-setting for the week and the day</p> <p>​ - <strong>3:20 PM:</strong> Optional progress check-in to share updates or adjust goals</p> <p>​ - <strong>4:40 PM:</strong> Wrap-up with optional demos or reflections on completed tasks</p> <p>Over the last few months, I’ve been getting more and more interested in two AI-related topics: <strong>AI-assisted coding</strong> and <strong>AI Agents</strong>. I haven’t done a good job at making time to dive into these topics, so I decided to use these co-working sessions to make time for that.</p> <p>This week I’ll start with AI-assisted coding. I’m starting from scratch, so my first step was to ask my friends on the Builders Club slack if they can recommend any workflows and tools to get me started. Here were some responses:</p> <blockquote> <p>you can play around here it’s fun if you want to get something visual before moving into a code based tool: https://lovable.dev/</p> </blockquote> <blockquote> <p>Chatgpt to write a product scope<br/> feed it into- https://v0.dev<br/> take the code and scope document and drop it into https://www.cursor.com<br/> if you want to skip set up might be useful https://codesandbox.io/<br/> (not perfect but cld work!)</p> </blockquote> <blockquote> <p>As always, it depends on “What’s your goal”.<br/> If you’re thinking about doing “website-y” stuff, Claude has better support for getting things to work with Javascript and playing with them right in the web browser.<br/> ChatGPT just launched “canvas” which does the same thing with Python code, but GUIs aren’t possible there. It’s best for data analysis,<br/> In both of those options you have a tool that “writes the code for me” but you still have to get it out of those things to get it to run “the way you want it”. There’s a lot of copy/pasting back and forth between those tools and your IDE.<br/> Cursor is arguably the best right now as a VS Code replacement that puts the AI right alongside your code and can work on the errors and bugs as you run them.<br/> If I was going to do more than a “light” amount of coding, I would jump into Cursor.</p> </blockquote> <blockquote> <p>I’ve been running ollama locally then using the Continue IntelliJ plugin to select the models. Then I download models from huggingface.</p> </blockquote> <p>I ordered these in terms of what seems to me to be order of difficulty.</p> <p>(Update: during the co-working session, someone also suggested https://www.continue.dev as a VS code plugin).</p> <p>My goal for the session is to explore a few of the tools mentioned above and come up with a concrete proposal for a project to start building in the next co-working session.</p> <p>Let’s go!</p> <h1 id="loveable">Loveable</h1> <p>Ok, it looks very nice. It seems like I can just start typing stuff into this text box.</p> <figure> <center> <img src="/assets/img/24-12-11-01.png" alt="test" style="width:100%; height:auto;"/> </center> </figure> <p>Let’s start with a website idea that’s been floating around in my head. Let’s try: </p> <figure> <center> <img src="/assets/img/24-12-11-03.png" alt="test" style="width:100%; height:auto;"/> </center> </figure> <p>Let’s see what happens when I hit “go”. Ok, I have to log in. I don’t have an account, but it looks like I can log in with GitHub, so let’s try that. That was easy. Now I can hit “go” again.</p> <p>It’s taking a few mins to think. Looks like it’s generating a bunch of code files that I’m not familiar with.</p> <figure> <center> <img src="/assets/img/24-12-11-02.png" alt="test" style="width:100%; height:auto;"/> </center> </figure> <p>Ok, wow, there is a website. It’s got two carousels on it. I can click on one and it gives me a new page.</p> <figure> <center> <img src="/assets/img/24-12-11-04.png" alt="test" style="width:100%; height:auto;"/> </center> </figure> <p>The carousels I make have a portrait aspect ratio, so I might see if I can get it to change that. There is a box for me to request a change.</p> <blockquote> <p>My carousels are going to have a portrait aspect ratio. Can you change the design to reflect that. Can you also showcase three carousels on the home page?</p> </blockquote> <p>Ok, it made them the right aspect ratio, but they are too big. Let’s try another request.</p> <blockquote> <p>Can you make the thumbnails smaller?</p> </blockquote> <p>Ok, so it seems like I can get it to make some changes, and it responds to them, but it’s not perfect.</p> <figure> <center> <img src="/assets/img/24-12-11-05.png" alt="test" style="width:100%; height:auto;"/> </center> </figure> <p>The search functionality seems to work though, so that’s cool.</p> <figure> <center> <img src="/assets/img/24-12-11-06.png" alt="test" style="width:100%; height:auto;"/> </center> </figure> <p>There is a GitHub button. Looks like I can transfer the code to GitHub. Let’s try that.</p> <p>Ok, crazy, it just made <a href="https://github.com/abranczyk/slide-surfboard">this GitHub repo</a> with my website on it.</p> <p>It looks like I can edit this code locally and then publish it through Loveable. I’ll come back to editing it later.</p> <p>For now, let’s publish. You can see what how the site looks <a href="https://slide-surfboard.lovable.app">here</a>. You can see that search works, and you can click on a carousel and click through the slides.</p> <p>Obviously it’s not amazing, but quite remarkable that the AI generated this from a few lines of prompt.</p> <h1 id="chatgpt--v0">ChatGPT + v0</h1> <p>Typing this into ChatGPT:</p> <blockquote> <p>I want to create a website. I will start with getting you to help me create the product scope. I will then feed it into https://v0.dev, then take the code and scope document and drop it into https://www.cursor.com. <br/> Here is what I want to do. Can you help me create the product scope?<br/> Create a static website where I can showcase educational carousels (slideshows). The website should have search functionality based on topics. The website should have the ability to browse carousels. It should be mobile native.</p> </blockquote> <p>You can see what ChatGPT came up with in Appendix A. Pretty fancy if you ask me.</p> <p>What’s next? V0? Looks similar to Loveable.</p> <figure> <center> <img src="/assets/img/24-12-11-07.png" alt="test" style="width:100%; height:auto;"/> </center> </figure> <p>Let’s see what happens if I give it the Project Overview, Features and Requirements, and Technical Specifications from ChatGPT.</p> <p>Looks like I have to create an account. Let’s do it.</p> <p>So far similar behaviour to Loveable. Thinking, coding…</p> <figure> <center> <img src="/assets/img/24-12-11-08.png" alt="test" style="width:100%; height:auto;"/> </center> </figure> <p>Ok, we have a website!</p> <figure> <center> <img src="/assets/img/24-12-11-09.png" alt="test" style="width:100%; height:auto;"/> </center> </figure> <p>It’s definitely not as beautiful as the Loveable one, but that would need to be edited later anyway. The search doesn’t seem to work, but the browse functionality is pretty cool.</p> <p>You can view the deployed website <a href="https://dmf2l9kilwv8qqt7.vercel.app">here</a>. Getting the code to GitHub seems like it might be possible but not immediately obvious to me how you would do that.</p> <h1 id="editing-the-code">Editing the code</h1> <p>So I got as far as having two draft websites, both of which presumably have a code base I can edit. Now the plan is to try to edit those code bases. For that, I will get Cursor and see if AI can help with that too.</p> <h1 id="cursor">Cursor</h1> <figure> <center> <img src="/assets/img/24-12-11-10.png" alt="test" style="width:100%; height:auto;"/> </center> </figure> <p>You can log in using GitHub and then download the install files.</p> <p>That’s cool, when you install it, it imports your plugins and keybindings from VS Code.</p> <p>Now that I’ve installed Cursor, let’s clone the repo for the website that Loveable made for me.</p> <figure> <center> <img src="/assets/img/24-12-11-11.png" alt="test" style="width:100%; height:auto;"/> </center> </figure> <p>Ok, I have the code on my computer. Now what?</p> <p>Maybe ChatGPT knows.</p> <figure> <center> <img src="/assets/img/24-12-11-12.png" alt="test" style="width:100%; height:auto;"/> </center> </figure> <p>ChatGPT’s answer can be found in Appendix B. That might be a bit much for this session. Maybe I will try and get AI to help me make some edits to the code to improve how it looks.</p> <p>Actually, now that I think about it, even if I am able to edit it, how will I deploy it? I wonder if making changes to the code and pushing it to the repo will actually be reflected in the website deployed by Loveable.</p> <p>Actually, my other websites that I made with jekyll lets me serve the website locally.</p> <p>Maybe I should try and see if the AI assistant can help me figure out if I can serve this website locally (be able to view it in my browser). Let’s try the chat feature.</p> <figure> <center> <img src="/assets/img/24-12-11-18.png" alt="test" style="width:100%; height:auto;"/> </center> </figure> <p>Ok, I won’t bore you with the whole exchnage, but I tried what the AI assistant suggested and every time something didn’t work, I pasted the error into the chat, and it told me what to try next.</p> <figure> <center> <img src="/assets/img/24-12-11-14.png" alt="test" style="height:180px; width:auto;"/><img src="/assets/img/24-12-11-15.png" alt="test" style="height:180px; width:auto;"/><img src="/assets/img/24-12-11-17.png" alt="test" style="height:180px; width:auto;"/> </center> </figure> <p>Essentially I needed to install some packages. The kind of thing that used to take a day of googling errors and reading through multiple Stack Exchange answers just took 5 minutes. I was able to serve the website locally. Neat!</p> <figure> <center> <img src="/assets/img/24-12-11-16.png" alt="test" style="width:100%; height:auto;"/> </center> </figure> <p>I only have ten mins left in this co-working session, so let’s see if I can get the AI to help me make a change to the website.</p> <p>Dang. Out of time. I also don’t have time to write up how the conversation went, but I managed to get it to help me figure out how to make the thumbnails smaller, so that’s cool!</p> <figure> <center> <img src="/assets/img/24-12-11-19.png" alt="test" style="width:100%; height:auto;"/> </center> </figure> <p>So my plan for next week’s session is to work on making this website much more beautiful and doing what I want it to do.</p> <hr/> <h1 id="appendix-a">Appendix A</h1> <h3 id="product-scope-for-static-website-to-showcase-educational-carousels">Product Scope for Static Website to Showcase Educational Carousels</h3> <h4 id="project-overview">Project Overview</h4> <p>The objective is to create a static website to showcase educational carousels (slideshows) with essential features to enhance user experience. The website should allow users to search for carousels by topics, browse through available carousels, and offer a mobile-native experience.</p> <h3 id="features-and-requirements">Features and Requirements</h3> <h4 id="1-carousel-showcase">1. Carousel Showcase</h4> <ul> <li><strong>Purpose:</strong> Display educational carousels in an engaging and visually appealing manner.</li> <li><strong>Requirements:</strong> <ul> <li>A dedicated section to display featured carousels on the homepage.</li> <li>Individual pages for each carousel, with a brief description and navigation controls for users to explore the slides.</li> </ul> </li> </ul> <h4 id="2-search-functionality">2. Search Functionality</h4> <ul> <li><strong>Purpose:</strong> Enable users to search for carousels based on topics.</li> <li><strong>Requirements:</strong> <ul> <li>Search bar prominently displayed on the homepage and other relevant pages.</li> <li>Search filters to refine results (e.g., by date added, topic, or popularity).</li> <li>Instant search suggestions while typing.</li> </ul> </li> </ul> <h4 id="3-browsing-capability">3. Browsing Capability</h4> <ul> <li><strong>Purpose:</strong> Allow users to discover carousels by exploring the library.</li> <li><strong>Requirements:</strong> <ul> <li>A “Browse” page displaying carousels categorized by topics.</li> <li>Sorting options (e.g., alphabetical, most viewed, recently added).</li> <li>Pagination or infinite scrolling for seamless browsing.</li> </ul> </li> </ul> <h4 id="4-mobile-native-design">4. Mobile-Native Design</h4> <ul> <li><strong>Purpose:</strong> Ensure a smooth user experience on mobile devices.</li> <li><strong>Requirements:</strong> <ul> <li>Fully responsive design, optimized for different screen sizes.</li> <li>Touch-friendly carousel navigation.</li> <li>Lightweight and fast-loading interface.</li> </ul> </li> </ul> <h4 id="5-static-website-architecture">5. Static Website Architecture</h4> <ul> <li><strong>Purpose:</strong> Maintain simplicity and speed with static content delivery.</li> <li><strong>Requirements:</strong> <ul> <li>Built using a static site generator (e.g., Gatsby, Next.js, or Hugo).</li> <li>Hosted on platforms optimized for static websites (e.g., Netlify, Vercel).</li> <li>Minimal use of JavaScript for critical functionality.</li> </ul> </li> </ul> <h4 id="6-additional-features-future-considerations">6. Additional Features (Future Considerations)</h4> <ul> <li><strong>User Accounts:</strong> Optional user accounts to bookmark or save favorite carousels.</li> <li><strong>Analytics Integration:</strong> Track user interactions and popular carousels.</li> <li><strong>Theming:</strong> Support for light and dark modes.</li> </ul> <h3 id="technical-specifications">Technical Specifications</h3> <ul> <li><strong>Tech Stack:</strong> <ul> <li>Frontend: HTML, CSS, JavaScript (if needed), and a static site generator.</li> <li>Hosting: Netlify, Vercel, or GitHub Pages.</li> <li>Search: Client-side search using JavaScript or a service like Algolia.</li> </ul> </li> <li><strong>Design Guidelines:</strong> <ul> <li>Clean, modern, and professional layout.</li> <li>Typography and color scheme to ensure readability.</li> <li>Consistent navigation across devices.</li> </ul> </li> </ul> <h3 id="deliverables">Deliverables</h3> <ol> <li><strong>Design Mockups:</strong> Wireframes and high-fidelity mockups for key pages (Homepage, Browse, Carousel Detail Page).</li> <li><strong>Static Website Code:</strong> Complete source code for the website.</li> <li><strong>Documentation:</strong> Instructions on updating content and deploying the website.</li> </ol> <h3 id="timeline">Timeline</h3> <ul> <li><strong>Week 1:</strong> Gather requirements and finalize design.</li> <li><strong>Week 2:</strong> Develop core features (homepage, carousel display, and search).</li> <li><strong>Week 3:</strong> Implement browsing functionality and optimize for mobile.</li> <li><strong>Week 4:</strong> Final testing and deployment.</li> </ul> <h3 id="success-metrics">Success Metrics</h3> <ul> <li>Website loads within 2 seconds on mobile.</li> <li>Users can find carousels using the search functionality within 3 clicks.</li> <li>Mobile usability score above 90% (e.g., using Google Lighthouse).</li> </ul> <hr/> <h1 id="appendix-b">Appendix B</h1> <p>Your friend’s suggestion to “feed the scope document into Cursor” likely means using Cursor to integrate your scope document into the workflow of improving the codebase. Cursor is a tool designed to assist with coding tasks, often leveraging AI to understand and refine code. Here’s how you might approach this:</p> <h3 id="1-understand-the-scope-documents-role">1. <strong>Understand the Scope Document’s Role</strong></h3> <ul> <li>A <strong>scope document</strong> outlines the goals, features, functionality, and requirements of the project. It serves as a blueprint for what the website should do and how it should perform.</li> <li>By “feeding” it into Cursor, the idea is to use the scope document to guide Cursor in aligning the codebase with your desired outcomes.</li> </ul> <h3 id="2-how-to-use-cursor-with-the-scope-document">2. <strong>How to Use Cursor with the Scope Document</strong></h3> <p>Cursor can help you:</p> <ul> <li>Understand how the existing codebase aligns with the scope document.</li> <li>Identify areas where the codebase is incomplete or deviates from the specified requirements.</li> <li>Refactor or add code to fulfill the scope requirements.</li> </ul> <p>Here’s how you can proceed:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Open the Codebase</strong>: Open your cloned codebase in Cursor, as you’ve already done.</li> <li><strong>Reference the Scope Document</strong>: <ul> <li>If Cursor supports direct input of natural language files, upload or paste the content of the scope document into the interface.</li> <li>Alternatively, summarize the key points from the scope document and enter them as comments or tasks in Cursor.</li> </ul> </li> <li><strong>Ask Cursor for Help</strong>: <ul> <li>Use AI prompts to clarify what needs to be implemented or improved. For example: <ul> <li>“Refactor the login functionality to meet the requirements described in this scope document.”</li> <li>“Add a feature for user registration, as detailed in the attached scope document.”</li> </ul> </li> </ul> </li> </ul> <h3 id="3-enhance-collaboration-between-scope-and-code">3. <strong>Enhance Collaboration Between Scope and Code</strong></h3> <ul> <li><strong>Map Scope to Code</strong>: For each feature or requirement in the scope document, locate the corresponding code or note where it needs to be added.</li> <li><strong>Iterative Feedback</strong>: Ask Cursor to analyze specific sections of the codebase to ensure they match the scope document. For example: <ul> <li>“Is the navigation bar implemented as described in the scope?”</li> <li>“Suggest improvements for SEO optimization according to these requirements.”</li> </ul> </li> </ul> <h3 id="4-output">4. <strong>Output</strong></h3> <p>Cursor can help you generate, review, or debug code that aligns better with the goals outlined in your scope document.</p> <p>If you’re unsure about the integration or Cursor’s capabilities, you could experiment by asking Cursor directly:</p> <blockquote> <p>“How can I integrate this scope document into my workflow to improve this codebase?”</p> </blockquote>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Getting started with AI-assisted coding]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Should you incorporate your one-person business?</title><link href="https://aggiebranczyk.com/blog/2024/should-you-incorporate-your-one-person-business/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Should you incorporate your one-person business?"/><published>2024-11-30T17:58:32+00:00</published><updated>2024-11-30T17:58:32+00:00</updated><id>https://aggiebranczyk.com/blog/2024/should-you-incorporate-your-one-person-business</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://aggiebranczyk.com/blog/2024/should-you-incorporate-your-one-person-business/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Why I did, and how.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Making a company website</title><link href="https://aggiebranczyk.com/blog/2024/making-a-company-website/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Making a company website"/><published>2024-10-22T18:59:49+00:00</published><updated>2024-10-22T18:59:49+00:00</updated><id>https://aggiebranczyk.com/blog/2024/making-a-company-website</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://aggiebranczyk.com/blog/2024/making-a-company-website/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A look at goals, tech, design, and content for the new ABE landing page]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Causal inference yesterday, today and tomorrow: a talk by Ilya Shpitser, Johns Hopkins University</title><link href="https://aggiebranczyk.com/blog/2024/causal-inference-ilya-shpitser/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Causal inference yesterday, today and tomorrow: a talk by Ilya Shpitser, Johns Hopkins University"/><published>2024-10-08T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-10-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://aggiebranczyk.com/blog/2024/causal-inference-ilya-shpitser</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://aggiebranczyk.com/blog/2024/causal-inference-ilya-shpitser/"><![CDATA[<p><em>The content of this post is based on a lecture given by Ilya Shpitser. The ideas presented are his. This post reflects my personal interpretation and understanding of the material. Any errors or omissions are my own.</em></p> <p><em>Recorded at Perimeter Institute, as part of a monthly webinar series jointly hosted by Perimeter, IVADO, and Institut Courtois: <a href="https://pirsa.org/24090157">https://pirsa.org/24090157</a>.</em></p> <h2 id="causal-inference">Causal inference</h2> <p>In causal inference, we imagine different “what-if” scenarios—what if an intervention happens, what if it doesn’t—and study the potential outcomes that might result from each scenario to understand the cause-effect relationship.</p> <h2 id="top-down-and-bottom-up-approaches">Top-down and bottom-up approaches</h2> <p>Consider two luminaries from the 1740s: David Hume and James Lind. David Hume was a <em>methods</em> person, sitting in his armchair, like a philosopher does, trying to figure out a good definition of causality. James Lind was an <em>applications</em> person, running the first ever randomized trials to find the cure for scurvy.</p> <p>These two people exemplify the two approaches to causal inference: <strong>top down</strong> and <strong>bottom up</strong>.</p> <p>Modern causal inference is a partnership between <strong>methods people</strong> and <strong>applications people</strong>. You need both because if you’re an applications person and you don’t have rigorous theory, you can do the wrong thing. And if you’re a theory person, without applications, you can go off in directions that aren’t connected to any real problems.</p> <h2 id="some-terminology--notation">Some terminology &amp; notation</h2> <p>In causal inference, we want to understand the effect of a particular action or intervention (the <em>cause</em>) on an outcome (the <em>effect</em>).</p> <p>We conceptualize cause-effect relationships by means of (<em>random variable</em>) responses to hypothetical interventions (also known as a <em>counterfactual</em><d-footnote>Things that didn't happen or are not the case.</d-footnote> <em>random variable</em> or a <em>potential outcome</em>).</p> <p>There are various notations for this, one of which is \(Y(a)\)<d-footnote>Some people write $Y_a$ or $Y^a$ instead.</d-footnote> which is read as “\(Y\) if \(A\)—possibly contrary to fact—had value \(a\)”. This is a very important bit of notation.</p> <p>Note that it is very different from \(Y\vert a\) which reads “\(Y\)—if we observed A—to have value \(a\)”. This distinction is a mathematical reflection of the familiar saying that “correlation is not causation”.</p> <p>The way people think about cause-effect relationships is in terms of hypothetical interventions that set a cause whose effect we’re interested in to a particular value (hypothetically), set it to a different value (hypothetically), and compare the outcomes. <strong>This is useful in real-life scenarios, where you are unable to do randomized trials.</strong> So you do this kind of special massaging of the data, which we call <em>adjusting for confounders</em>.</p> <h2 id="schools-of-thought">Schools of thought</h2> <p>There are at least two schools of thought on Causal Modelling: <em>Potential outcomes</em> and <em>Causal Graphs</em>. Potential outcomes specifies causal assumptions algebraically, emphasizes (potentially counterfactual) random variables, and is common in statistics and public health. Causal graphs specifies causal assumptions graphically, emphasizes operators (eg the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">do()</code> operator) and structural equations, and is common in computer science (and CMU <nobr>philosophy<d-footnote>As well as intellectual descendants, of which there are many (Caltech, Columbia, Univeristy of Waterloo, etc.)</d-footnote>)</nobr>. The frameworks turn out to be complementary and a unification exists based on <em>Single World Intervention Graphs</em> (SWIG). <d-footnote>There was a <a href="https://pirsa.org/24090084">talk by Thomas Richardson</a> about this unification the following week at Causalworlds.</d-footnote></p> <figure> <img src="/assets/img/IMG_9DD37D6CB663-1.jpeg" alt="test" style="width:100%; height:auto;"/> </figure> <h2 id="the-modern-causal-inference-pipeline">The modern causal inference pipeline</h2> <p><em>(From Ilya’s POV)</em></p> <p>Start by talking to somebody who does applications, come up with a cause-effect question of interest, then try to express it mathematically in terms of a causal parameter, usually as a hypothetical experiment, such as the average causal effect<d-footnote>AKA the <i>average treatment effect</i>, measures the difference in mean outcomes between units assigned to the treatment and units assigned to the control (source: <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Average_treatment_effect">Wikipedia</a>).</d-footnote>.</p> <p>Elicit a causal model—which encodes assumptions we’re willing to make about the problem—from an expert, or possibly learn the model from data.</p> <p>Do <em>identification</em>, which means asking if a causal parameter can be uniquely expressible in terms of available data given the causal model. This is basically checking that the observed data likelihood that we have in the problem actually has information that can be brought to bear on what we’re asking. That’s very important.</p> <p>If the parameter can be expressed in terms of observed data, we think about estimation, or statistical inference, or learning (if we’re a machine learning person). This means we ask how we can construct a procedure that makes a good guess about our identified parameter from data. We might be concerned with doing it efficiently or doing it robustly.</p> <p>Causal parameters are generally <em>counterfactual</em>. Because of this, it’s very difficult to validate whether we did a good job estimating them (unlike in machine learning and supervised learning problems where validation can be accomplished using, eg, holdout data<d-footnote>A portion of historical, labeled data that is held out of the data sets used for training and validating (source: <a href="https://c3.ai/glossary/data-science/holdout-data/">c3.ai</a>).</d-footnote>). So the emphasis on causal inference is on robustness of procedures to violations of assumptions, sensitivity analysis, etc.</p> <p>Quantifying uncertainty is important, which can be done by confidence intervals or credible intervals.</p> <h2 id="connections-between-causal-inference-and-missing-data">Connections between causal inference and missing data</h2> <p>Causal inference is a version of a missing data problem. Vice versa, you can think about missing data problems causally.</p> <p>In causal inference, the fundamental object is:</p> <blockquote> <p>What would be the outcome if, hypothetically, I set the treatment to some value, possibly contrary to fact.</p> </blockquote> <p>In missing data, we are interested in:</p> <blockquote> <p>What would be the outcome if we could hypothetically observe it, even though in reality it may be missing.</p> </blockquote> <p>The principled methods from missing data have a strong relationship to principled methods from causal inference. They are kind of sister disciplines.</p> <h2 id="what-machine-learning-and-causal-inference-communities-can-learn-from-each-other">What Machine Learning and Causal Inference communities can learn from each other</h2> <h3 id="constructive-optimism-vs-constructive-pessimism">Constructive optimism vs. constructive pessimism</h3> <p>Machine learning (ML) is a very optimistic field. They have a “let’s just build it and see if it works” attitude, even if they can’t prove it will always work, which is admirable. They publish quickly and often, and the progress is clear, as the recently-developed large language models (LLMs) have shown.</p> <p>Causal inference (CI) people, on the other hand, are conservative and constructively pessimistic. Since it’s difficult for them to validate their results, they assume that they are wrong by default. They spend a lot of time thinking about: robust methods; validation; sensitivity analysis (checking if violating their assumptions still gives them the answer they expect). This is a valuable attitude in applied problems, where things don’t work the way you would expect.</p> <h3 id="finite-sample-vs-asymptotic-results">Finite sample vs. asymptotic results</h3> <p>ML people tend to think about finite sample results. CI people tend to think about asymptotic identification and estimation results. These are good complements to each other<d-footnote>Side note: a similar discussion is happening in Quantum Optimization. See eg <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.02279">here</a>. </d-footnote>.</p> <h3 id="validation-vs-transparency">Validation vs. transparency</h3> <p>People in ML emphasize tasks and validation of results, which is very useful. On the other hand, people in CI aren’t able to validate their findings (you can’t observe things that didn’t happen), so they try to be very transparent about their assumptions and put them upfront. Both are very important to how we should do science.</p> <h3 id="semi-parametric-theory-and-predictive-performance">Semi-parametric theory and predictive performance</h3> <p>Causal inference people know that often the best way to approach problems with infinite-dimensional parameters is to use semi-parameteric theory. A lot of folks in ML aren’t aware of this. Ilya believes that semi-parametric theory is the correct approach for many problems that arise in ML, such as problems in model based reinforcement learning for example.</p> <p>In saying that, people in ML have thought about predictive modelling really hard for the last 50 years and they have excellent predictive performance. This can be very helpful as a subroutine for semi-parametric<d-footnote><b>ML definitions:</b> A fully parametric model is a model where the number of parameters is fixed (eg linear regression model). A non-parametric model is a model where the number of parameters grows with how much data you have (eg random forest). A semi-parametric model is in between. <b>Formal statistical theory definitions:</b> Statistical models are all about the tangent space. The tangent space is the space of scores, where a score is the derivative of the log-likelihood wrt the parameters. A lot of the behaviour of learning has to do with the tangent space. A parametric model is when the tangent space is Euclidian because the number of dimensions equals the number of parameters—they are just fixed. Semi-parametric models have infinite dimensional tangent spaces with equality restrictions. If you want to do ML, you are in the semi-parametric regime. There you have very wiggly, flexible surfaces, and you can not do linear regression—you have to use big neural networks. </d-footnote> inference of causal effects.</p> <h3 id="parameter-identifiability">Parameter identifiability</h3> <p>People in CI worry about parameter identifiability, which is the very important problem of determining if your data has information about your problem. In ML, there are some model fragility issues related to the fact that parameters in ML are not identified because the models are over-parameterized (deep learning systems have billions of parameters).</p> <h3 id="unsupervised-problems">Unsupervised problems</h3> <p>CI isn’t a supervised problem, so CI people have developed principled ways of thinking about problems that are unsupervised. Many problems in ML also go beyond the traditional supervised framework, even though they are sometimes approached as if they were purely supervised. For example, in a prediction task, if some outcomes are unobserved, this becomes a missing data issue, which shifts the problem away from a strictly supervised setting. Acknowledging these nuances can help both fields refine their approaches.</p> <h3 id="causal-language">Causal language</h3> <p>Causal language is very helpful when thinking about model stability, invariance, fairness, interpretability. This has been noticed in a lot of ML papers that use CI.</p> <h3 id="missing-data">Missing data</h3> <p>CI and missing data are sister disciplines, so causal methods give you principled approaches for thinking about missing data. This is particularly important since most applied analyses will inevitably encounter some degree of missing data. In practice, it’s common to see quick fixes, such as using a standard imputation package in Python or R. But it’s crucial to go beyond thinking of missing data as a data cleaning issue. Different types of missingness require different strategies.</p> <h3 id="powerful-optimization-methods">Powerful optimization methods</h3> <p>People in ML have powerful optimization methods which are likely helpful for solving estimating equations that arise in semi-parametric inference.</p> <h3 id="surprisingly-many-but-not-all-problems-are-regression-problems">Surprisingly many, but not all, problems are regression problems</h3> <p>A big lesson from ML is that surprisingly many problems in life are regression problems, which neural networks are well-suited to handle.</p> <p>But it’s important to acknowledge that not every problem can be approached as a regression problem. While LLMs have generated excitement due to their impressive capabilities, there’s a growing realization that they have limitations. For example, LLMs can sometimes produce misleading or overly optimistic responses and may struggle with highly structured problems, such as proofs, chess, or tasks involving causal inference. This isn’t surprising, as different types of problems—like planning, logical reasoning, and causal inference—have specialized methods that are better suited to their unique demands. LLMs, despite their advanced transformer architectures, are not designed to excel at every type of problem, and it’s important to apply the right tools to the right challenges.</p> <h2 id="the-elevator-pitch-for-why-we-do-causal-inference">The elevator pitch for why we do causal inference</h2> <p>Causal inference can be used to emulate randomized control trials in cases where its either unethical (like medicine) or too expensive (like in economics<d-footnote>In economics, you think about large scale policy changes which are hard to test. </d-footnote>)<d-footnote>Or impossible? Like astrophysics?</d-footnote>.</p> <p>But it’s not like you get this for free. You get this by making assumptions about the causal model. Those assumptions might not be exactly right so you have to be upfront about your assumptions and pitch your result as: if you believe this list of assumptions, then this is our conclusion, but if you do not, then you should believe it less.</p> <h2 id="what-else-did-ilya-cover-in-the-talk-that-didnt-make-it-into-my-notes">What else did Ilya cover in the talk that didn’t make it* into my notes?</h2> <p><em>(*not because it’s any less interesting, just not where my head is at right now)</em></p> <ul> <li>The state of the art in causal inference</li> <li>An example of the causal inference pipeline on a project he is working on with cardiac surgeons</li> <li>Open problems in causal inference</li> <li>State of the art with “post-selected data”, which means something different in causal inference and quantum information communities (during question time)</li> <li>Areas for collaboration between ML &amp; CI (during question time)</li> <li>How causal language lets you assess stability (during question time)</li> </ul> <h2 id="should-you-watch-the-talk">Should you watch the talk?</h2> <p>It’s a really nice talk. I recommend it. You can watch it <a href="https://pirsa.org/24090157">here</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name>Aggie Branczyk</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[My notes on select parts of the talk, in particular, what Machine Learning and Causal Inference communities can learn from each other.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Nice company, but what does it do?</title><link href="https://aggiebranczyk.com/blog/2024/nice-company-but-what-does-it-do/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Nice company, but what does it do?"/><published>2024-10-05T14:04:20+00:00</published><updated>2024-10-05T14:04:20+00:00</updated><id>https://aggiebranczyk.com/blog/2024/nice-company-but-what-does-it-do</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://aggiebranczyk.com/blog/2024/nice-company-but-what-does-it-do/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A vision for Aggie Branczyk Enterprises]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">October Update: What’s happening at Academics in the Wild</title><link href="https://aggiebranczyk.com/blog/2024/october-update-whats-happening-at-academics-in-the-wild/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="October Update: What’s happening at Academics in the Wild"/><published>2024-10-01T15:35:33+00:00</published><updated>2024-10-01T15:35:33+00:00</updated><id>https://aggiebranczyk.com/blog/2024/october-update-whats-happening-at-academics-in-the-wild</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://aggiebranczyk.com/blog/2024/october-update-whats-happening-at-academics-in-the-wild/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Upcoming events, podcast throwback series, update on members zoom calls, and highlights from our previous AMA.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Physicist back from the wild</title><link href="https://aggiebranczyk.com/blog/2024/physicist-back-from-the-wild/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Physicist back from the wild"/><published>2024-09-29T02:30:37+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-29T02:30:37+00:00</updated><id>https://aggiebranczyk.com/blog/2024/physicist-back-from-the-wild</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://aggiebranczyk.com/blog/2024/physicist-back-from-the-wild/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Reflections on attending an academic conference, how companies are funded, and maker-spaces for experimental physics]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Book review: The Geek Way by Andrew McAfee</title><link href="https://aggiebranczyk.com/blog/2024/book-review-the-geek-way/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Book review: The Geek Way by Andrew McAfee"/><published>2024-09-23T10:08:01+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-23T10:08:01+00:00</updated><id>https://aggiebranczyk.com/blog/2024/book-review-the-geek-way</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://aggiebranczyk.com/blog/2024/book-review-the-geek-way/"><![CDATA[<figure> <img src="/assets/img/bureaucracy.webp" alt="test" style="width:100%; height:auto;"/> <figcaption style="text-align: center;">The soft bureaucracy of overcommunication</figcaption> </figure> <p>My first thought after finishing this book was: I wonder how hard it would be to create a website called <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">shouldhavebeenablogpost.com</code>\(^1\) where its only purpose is for users to vote on whether a book should have been a blogpost or not.</p> <p>The Geek Way by Andrew McAfee should have been a blog post.</p> <p>In saying that, there were a couple of absolute gems that really stood out for me, which made the book worthwhile. But before we get to those, what is the book about?</p> <p>The book is about the ways in which the Silicon Valley “geeks” run their modern-tech-era companies, and why those ways are better than the ways in which non-Silicon-Valley non-geeks run their industrial-era companies.</p> <p>The author distills those ways into four principles, which he calls the <strong>Four Geek Mantras</strong>:</p> <ul> <li>Science: Argue about evidence</li> <li>Ownership: Align, then unleash</li> <li>Speed: Iterate with feedback</li> <li>Openness: Reflect, don’t defend</li> </ul> <p>Principles 1 and 3 are pretty obvious to anyone with some interest in Silicon Valley tech companies (Principle 1 says use data to make decisions while Principle 3 says use agile over waterfall).</p> <p>Principle 4 says that people respond to peer pressure, so make sure the peers in your company pressure each other to do things that are aligned with the values of the company.</p> <p>Principle 2 is interesting though. It’s about bureaucracy and how it sucks. That’s no surprise to anyone. But McAfee’s explanation for where it comes from is gold:</p> <blockquote> <p>The ultimate explanation is that dense bureaucracy is the result of status seeking by us status-obsessed [humans]. <strong>We invent work so that we can be part of it.</strong> We strive to be consulted on lots of decisions, and if possible have veto power over them. Excess bureaucracy is a bug for anyone who wants a company to run efficiently, but it’s a feature for the [humans] who seek opportunities to gain status in the organization. \(^2\)</p> </blockquote> <p>I mean, intuitively I knew this, but I had never seen it spelled out so eloquently.</p> <p>But it gets better, because McAffee points out something I <em>didn’t</em> know, not even on an intuitive level. The way to prevent this kind of thing from happening is to <strong>create</strong> silos within the organization. Excuse me, what? My whole professional life, I had thought that the key to fixing organizations was to <strong>break down</strong> silos…to encourage communication. But McAfee makes a very good case for why the opposite is true: “cross-team communication can be harmful because it often turns into a soft form of bureaucracy.”</p> <p>But if you create silos and cut off communications between teams, how will people figure out what to? You make sure that the company’s high-level vision and strategy are clear and that everyone in the chain of command knows how to, and is incentivized to, translate that vision and strategy into clear team-level objectives and key results.</p> <p>I think we all know that clear vision and clear objectives would make our lives easier, but the point here is that they are absolutely critical if you want to avoid the <em>soft bureaucracy of over-communication</em>.</p> <p>The other thing in the book that stood out for me was in the discussion of Principle 4, the one about peer pressure. Specifically: how should we define a peer group?</p> <p>St. Augustine says <em>love</em>: “a people is an assemblage of reasonable beings bound together by a common agreement as to the objects of their love.”</p> <p>Anton Chekhov says <em>hate</em>: “love, friendship, respect do not unite people as much as common hatred for something.”</p> <p>Andrew McAffee says <em>norms</em>: “whether we love the people around us or hate them, what unites them and us into a coherent group is what we’ve collectively decided to punish with painful social rejection—with the threat or reality of ostracism from the group. A big part of what unites us, in other words, is our norms.”</p> <p>This piqued my interest in a different context from the one in which it was presented.</p> <p>I talk with a lot physics academics who are considering, or already pursuing, a career change from academia to industry. Due to the strong norms within academia, and the fear of ostracism, this kind of transition can be really traumatic for people. But then, after they leave and align themselves with a new group, it’s hard to remember what all the fuss was about. The discussion in this book shed some light on how this happens.</p> <h4 id="overall-verdict">Overall verdict</h4> <p>I felt that most of the book was pretty obvious and self-evident, and that most of the extended discussion of the four principles didn’t add much texture or depth to the high-level points.</p> <p>In saying that, there were a couple of gems that really stood out for me.</p> <p>So I think it was worth reading, but if I knew then what I know now, I would have read the one-page chapter summaries first and only dug into the parts of the book that seemed novel to me.</p> <p>What do you think? <br/></p> <hr/> <p>\(^1\) I checked and the domain was registered recently. I wonder what book triggered the owner to buy it!</p> <p>\(^2\) In the book, McAfee coined the term <em>Homo Ultrasocialis</em> which he uses to refer to humans, but I didn’t want to go into that here.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Could have been a blog post, but contains some absolute gems that make it worthwhile]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">September Update</title><link href="https://aggiebranczyk.com/blog/2024/september-update/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="September Update"/><published>2024-09-01T13:02:21+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-01T13:02:21+00:00</updated><id>https://aggiebranczyk.com/blog/2024/september-update</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://aggiebranczyk.com/blog/2024/september-update/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[What's happening at Academics in the Wild]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Builders Club @ the Startup Barn</title><link href="https://aggiebranczyk.com/blog/2024/builders-club-the-startup-barn/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Builders Club @ the Startup Barn"/><published>2024-08-28T18:25:49+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-28T18:25:49+00:00</updated><id>https://aggiebranczyk.com/blog/2024/builders-club--the-startup-barn</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://aggiebranczyk.com/blog/2024/builders-club-the-startup-barn/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Aggie Branczyk Enterprises moves into the Clubhouse]]></summary></entry></feed>